Finding Aid for Will Hathaway papers, 1980-2000
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Will Hathaway papers 1980-2000
Hathaway, Will.
0758 Aa 2
Will Hathaway, an Ann Arbor resident and University of Michigan graduate, is an activist mainly involved in peace and arms control issues. Hathaway's papers document his involvement in issues while a student at the University of Michigan, his involvement in the arms control lobby, and his efforts in organizing a 1999 community forum on nuclear weapons abolition.
2 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Material was received in March 2007 from Will Hathaway (donor no. 9370 )
Periodic additions to the records are not expected.
The collection is open to research.
Will Hathaway, an Ann Arbor resident and University of Michigan graduate, is an activist mainly involved in peace and arms control issues. Hathaway was involved in many political issues and student organizations while a student at the University of Michigan in the 1980s. He was a member of the Guild House Board of Directors and the LS&A student government. He formed the Michigan students for Anderson organization and helped campaign for John Anderson for the 1980 presidential election. In 1981, he conceived of and helped organize a forum on national security. He was also actively involved in the 1982 Michigan nuclear weapons freeze campaign.
After graduation, Hathaway worked for the Federation of American Scientists (FAS) in Washington, D.C. and became involved in arms control lobbying. In 1983, he helped form the Coalition for Arms Control for the Second Congressional District (Michigan), a group of grassroots organizations initially aimed at changing Representative Pursell's vote for the MX missile.
In 1999, Hathaway helped organize a community forum for nuclear weapons abolition, which aimed to foster discussion on nuclear weapons abolition through various lectures and panels.
Hathaway's papers document his involvement in issues while a student at the University of Michigan, his involvement in the arms control lobby, and his efforts in organizing a 1999 community forum on nuclear weapons abolition. His papers have been divided into three series: University of Michigan Activism, Arms Control Lobbying, and Nuclear Weapons Abolition Community Forum.
Subjects:
Hathaway, Will.; University of Michigan--Students--Political activity.; Guild House (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Peace movements--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Nuclear disarmament--Citizen participation.; MX (Weapons system); Pursell, Carl D.
- University of Michigan Activism 1980-1984, 1999-2000
  The University of Michigan Activism series (1980-1984, 1999-2000, 0.75 linear feet) covers Hathaway's involvement in different activist campaigns and organizations while at student at the University of Michigan. Materials include his involvement in the 1980 John Anderson presidential campaign, the Forum on National Security he helped organize, and his work on the 1982 nuclear weapons freeze campaign in Michigan. This series also includes some of his later work (1999-2000) with the Guild House.
  - "Art at Ground Zero: Artists' Statements on Nuclear War," 1983 (Box 1)
  - Bret Eynon and military recruitment at the University of Michigan 1982 (Box 1)
  - Budget cuts 1981-1983 (Box 1)
  - Civil defense pamphlet distribution 1983 (Box 1)
  - Forum on National Security 1980-1981
    - Teach-in that inspired the forum (Peace and Politics in the 1980s) (Box 1)
    - Early planning documents (Box 1)
    - Resumes of speakers and publicity planning (Box 1)
    - Background information on speakers (Box 1)
    - Flyers and posters (Box 1)
    - Financing (Box 1)
  - Guild House 1999-2000 (Box 1)
  - Guild House Board of Directors 1982-1983 (Box 1)
  - Nuclear free zone (Ann Arbor) 1984 (Box 1)
  - Nuclear weapons freeze campaign 1982 (Box 1)
  - Peace Task Force at First Presbyterian 1981-1983, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Progressive Student Coalition 1980 (Box 1)
  - Student government
    - LSA student government
      - Campaign materials 1980-1981 (Box 1)
      - Student participation in University decision making (Box 1)
    - MSA election materials (Box 1)
  - University of Michigan Students for Anderson 1980 (Box 1)
- Arms Control Lobbying 1984-1992
  The Arms Control Lobbying series (1984-1992, 0.5 linear feet) documents his involvement in the Arms Control Lobby while working for the Federation of American Scientists in Washington, D.C. Documents include information on the Coalition for Arms Control mostly covering their lobbying effort aimed at changing Representative Carl Pursell's vote for the MX missile. This series also includes Hathaway's master's thesis, which includes a chapter on the Coalition for Arms Control (CAC). Researchers interested in learning more about the background and goals of the CAC should consult this thesis.
  - Coalition for Arms Control (2nd Congressional District) 1985-1992, 1994-1996, 9 folders (Box 1)
  - Master's thesis: "Long-term Arms Control and Disarmament Coalitions" (includes chapter on Coalition for Arms Control-2nd Congressional District) (Box 2)
  - MX lobbying 1984
    - Grassroots information (Box 2)
    - Grassroots mailing (Box 2)
    - Lobbying materials (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
    - Press relations (Box 2)
    - Representative Pursell lobbying (Box 2)
    - Representative Pursell and call responses (Box 2)
    - Rough drafts and originals (Box 2)
  - MX rail garrison 1990 (Box 2)
- Nuclear Weapons Abolition Community Forum 1998-2000
  Nuclear Weapons Abolition Community Forum (1998-2000, 0.75 linear feet) includes materials on the planning, publicity and press, and outcomes of an October 1999 community forum on nuclear weapons abolition.
  - Alan Haber (planning) (Box 2)
  - City Council resolution (in support of the abolition of nuclear weapons) (Box 2)
  - Cosponsors (Box 2)
  - Follow-up (Box 2)
  - Hague appeal (Box 2)
  - Jonathan Schell project, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Peace Action and student activists (Box 2)
  - Peace and Environmental Coalition to Abolish Nuclear Weapons meeting minutes 1998-2000 (Box 2)
  - Planning (Box 2)
  - Press (Box 2)
  - Project Abolition, foundations (funding) (Box 2)
  - Publicity (Box 2)
  - Speakers
    - Arjun Makhijani (Box 2)
    - Bruce Blair (Box 2)
    - Merav Datan (Box 2)
    - Peace Science Society (Box 2)
    - Photographs (Box 2)
    - Planning (Box 2)
  - U.S. Campaign to Abolish Nuclear Weapons (Box 2)
  - University of Michigan support/cosponsors (Box 2)